The jungles of Yunnan,
southern China.
Life here is more surprising,
brighter and more bizarre
than almost anywhere
in the country.
Each species holds
extraordinary skills
to harvest
the jungle's bounty.
This is just one of many
diverse landscapes.
Full of rare
and surprising creatures.
For the first time,
we'll uncover
their remarkable untold stories...
In The Hidden Kingdoms of China.
This handsome devil
is the Asian hornbill.
And he's a family man.
For the next four months,
this super dad
will be the sole provider
for his family of three.
Mom's not lazy.
When it comes to parenting,
she is just as dedicated
as dad.
She enters her nest
before laying her eggs,
shedding her own flight feathers,
rendering her totally entombed.
Welcome to motherhood,
Asian hornbill style.
With dad often away hunting,
she needs this extreme measure
to hide her growing chicks
from nest raiders.
Hornbills bond for life.
Our pair is nesting
in this tree
for the tenth year straight.
Mom's only outlet
to the world
is a slit half an inch wide
in the tree hollow.
Wide enough for dad
to supply food
and narrow enough to keep
nest-raiding predators out.
Dad returns to the nest
multiple times a day.
He can deliver over
100 pieces of fruit
to his family each visit.
He stores the fruit
in a special pouch
at the base of his neck.
To pass the fruit onto mom,
he skillfully rolls each one
to the tip of his huge beak.
100 Feet up
from the jungle floor,
it's a mouth-to-mouth
precision operation, most of the time.
He's under intense pressure
to feed hungry mouths.
Sugary fruit alone
will not sustain his young.
Dad has to up his game.
A tiny owl chick,
a protein hit.
But then...
The meal falls all the way
to the jungle floor.
Retrieving it is too risky.
Dad has no choice
but to hunt again.
Mom waits anxiously.
He returns with a bigger chick.
A prize he can't afford to lose.
He crushes the bones
and tries again.
Too big!
But he's not giving up.
Success at last.
Thanks to super parents,
the chicks
will soon be ready to fledge.
It's not just our hornbills;
all creatures here
show ingenious adaptations
to this hidden kingdom.
But the jungle needs the animals
as much as the animals
need the jungle.
The Asian elephant.
Numbering only 300 in China,
they are elusive.
These gardeners of the jungle
help maintain
this hidden kingdom.
They have a huge appetite,
spending up to 18 hours a day
just eating.
These elephants devour
hundreds of pounds of plants.
They're not exactly
fussy eaters.
Just one part of the process
helping to preserve
a healthy jungle.
♪ ♪
Every time the herd moves on,
the elephants deposit
undigested seeds,
which pass through
their stomachs intact.
Piles of dung
scattered far and wide
through the jungle make
the perfect dispersal system
for vegetation.
Many trees here rely on animals
to spread their seeds.
And trees provide clean air,
shelter and food
to all who live here.
They are magnificent
silent heroes.
And yet we know few
of their stories.
This one is said to be
the largest banyan tree
in all of China;
a venerable 300 years old.
Out of its branches
thousands of aerial roots
spread in all directions.
From these, others sprout,
reaching for the ground,
thickening and forming
new trunks.
The crown covers
an astonishing 88,000 square feet,
the size of one and a half
American football fields.
This banyan is so big
that it's its own
one-tree forest.
Regarded as sacred,
people leave red banners
and lanterns as offerings,
in the belief they bring
happiness and good luck.
Covering an area
larger than California,
Yunnan is a unique part of China.
Home to over half
the entire country's plant species.
And yet, the jungles
shouldn't be here.
Mountains border the jungles,
keeping out the cold air
of winter heading south.
Deep, narrow valleys
funnel in warm, wet air,
making it one of the most northern
jungles in the world.
A secret realm
full of wildlife stories
about to be revealed
for the first time.
Mysterious animals hide
in remote corners of this kingdom.
Camera traps in China's
Yunnan jungle
capture surprising creatures.
A pair of marbled cats.
Footage of them in China
is extremely rare.
These shy creatures are
one of the least known
of the small wild cats.
Jungles make up less than 7%
of the Earth's surface,
yet are home to half
the world's
land-based plants and animals.
The perfect combination of light,
water, nutrients, and terrain
creates diversity
found nowhere else in China.
Life here should be easy.
Competition for these resources
is fierce,
so every animal adopts
its own clever survival strategy,
allowing a host of creatures
to live side by side.
From feathered friends......
To creepy crawlies,
mud-sucking butterflies
to honeybees,
the world's only
venomous primate......
To one of the largest
tree-living mammals
on the planet,
all have one thing
in common:
they've found ways to adapt
to this jungle environment.
A place where leaves
and branches
harbor the unimaginable.
In Yunnan, some of the coolest
creatures
are filmed here
for the first time.
With names that sound
like characters
plucked out of a comic book,
caterpillars are
marvels of nature.
This is Checkers,
named after
its geometric pattern
down its back.
Shaped like a shield,
this is, well, the Shield.
With a colored, nut-looking lump
in his middle,
this is Almondback.
And dressed to impress,
the Jester.
They're little known and many
are still undescribed by science.
Like high-vis vests,
bright colors are a warning sign
which predators need
to avoid at all costs.
Imitation, chemical weapons
and camouflage
are all tools
in the arsenal of survival
for these jungle caterpillars.
Thousands of nails
cover Pin Cushion.
The pink spots mounted
on his rear
consist of minute pins
that he inflates
when threatened,
to attack any predator
that crosses his path.
Dragon Head emerges
from the egg
with his horns complete,
ready to defend himself;
six in total.
The long, arching
outer pairs
lead to a central pointy crown
fit for a Chinese dragon.
Snake Head wears a mask,
complete with painted eyes.
All that airborne predators
are seeing
is a dangerous snake.
He can happily carry on
and feed.
But there's one
that predators truly fear...
Medusa.
Medusa is locked and loaded
with a halo
of stinging spines.
For her, it's all about defense.
Each razor-sharp spike
is a hollow needle
connected to a poison gland.
She's ready to inject a toxin
into any unlucky predator
that comes too close.
Those that don't use weapons
rely on camouflage,
like the twig caterpillar.
Legs set far apart,
he creates a characteristic loop
as he walks.
He can also make
like a statue,
remaining motionless
and undetected for days.
Others protect themselves
by building
some of the most intricate
constructions
in the animal kingdom.
Inside these leaves,
stuck together by her own silk,
is a living caterpillar
known as Witch's Hat.
To accommodate a growing body,
she adds to her hat,
leaf by leaf.
When she's an adult,
she'll become a wingless moth
full of eggs waiting
for a male to fertilize them.
This is her home for life.
She's even worked out
a way to discard her waste.
She gently balances her droppings
on tiny silk threads,
ready to jettison them
as far as she can.
All these caterpillars
have the need to eat
and not be eaten.
Stunning looks
and impressive adaptations
go a long way.
After hours of roaming
these jungle hillsides,
our herd is still eating.
Even in the heat of the day,
the elephants are geared up
for keeping cool.
They have few sweat glands,
but are equipped
with their own air-conditioning system.
Hair keeps most mammals warm,
but for these elephants
it does the opposite.
When hair covers the skin,
it acts as an insulator.
When sparse,
it dissipates heat,
cooling the bodies
of the herd
up to an extra 20%.
Stinging insects
have no problems
getting through the hair.
Elephants are thick-skinned,
but more sensitive
than they look.
The herd feels every bite.
Flapping ears help,
but there is a better solution.
They spray themselves with dust
to keep annoying insects
and parasite numbers down.
It also acts
as elephant sunscreen.
And besides,
dust bathing is just fun.
Any excuse for this youngster
to roll in the dirt.
When the fun is over, the herd
needs to head somewhere special.
A tricky journey to the bottom
of the valley lies ahead.
The herd has mastered
a system
which stops them careering down
the slippery slopes.
Placing all weight
on their front feet,
they bend their hind legs
to slow them down.
Not exactly mountain goats,
but more than capable
of tackling the steep terrain.
This is their destination.
Where the river slows,
mineral-rich sediment settles.
The elephant's gold.
Salt and nutrients
concentrate right here,
and our elephants know it.
The herd has the knowledge
and the tools
to access what it needs.
The elephants dig up potassium,
sodium and phosphorus-rich salts,
essential for maintaining
muscle function.
Their trunks alone are made up
of 150,000 bundles
of muscle fibers.
Helping them to suck up gallons
of this life-giving water.
But elephants aren't the only
mineral diggers around here.
Someone else is watching
their every step.
Jungle jade follows
in the footsteps of the elephant herd.
A swallowtail, named after
those swallow-like forked hind wings.
Butterflies often gather
at the river's edge,
in a behavior
known as mud puddling.
It's exactly what you think.
Still water
in the elephant's footprints is ideal.
Little is known about mud puddling,
but we do know some things.
Most of the butterflies found
around the puddles are males,
and scientists believe
they're after the salts.
He uses a long, hollow tube
that's part of his mouth
to extract precious nutrients,
which he will pass on
to his partner during mating.
The rest he expels.
This boost of nutrients improves
the viability of the female's eggs,
increasing the couple's chances
of passing on their genes
to the next generation.
Some young in these jungles
get a different kind
of parental gift.
A male crested treeswift.
An exposed branch
offers an easy takeoff,
but here he also hides
an extraordinary nest.
It's just one and a half
inches wide
and a perfect fit
for one precious egg.
The next three weeks
are dad's most important,
because in this nest
is his only chick,
just a few days old.
So vulnerable,
she should never be left alone
until she can fly the nest.
Her survival is all
about teamwork.
Dad needs his partner.
While one is nest-sitting,
the other is airborne.
Hunting insects to feed
their growing chick.
From a special pouch
in the back of her throat,
mom regurgitates a food ball
containing hundreds of insects,
hoping to satisfy
her chick's constant appetite.
Through thick and thin,
mom and dad continuously
swap duties......
No matter what the jungle weather
throws at them.
As the rain begins to fall,
mom takes the first shift.
The conditions become more severe,
leaving dad with the baby.
Spreading out
his breast feathers,
he does his best
to shelter her.
Neither mom nor dad have
successfully hunted during the rain.
Wet weather means there are
fewer flying insects to catch.
Once the sky is clear,
both parents must find food.
Abandoning the nest
leaves our chick alone and defenseless.
Mom and dad have no choice
but to hunt
at the same time,
leaving their chick exposed.
Instinct tells her
to stay absolutely still.
If she does,
her incredible camouflage
might just be enough
to keep her alive.
As soon as mom returns,
our chick feels safe to move again.
She has survived the first tests
on her journey to independence.
It's a proud parent moment.
The jungle never sleeps.
Hunters stalk the night.
They must use the darkness
to get the food they need.
The clock is ticking.
A slow loris,
known in China
as the bee monkey.
The world's only
venomous primate......
With a bite that may
protect them
against predators.
The slow loris has evolved
special blood vessels
in his wrists and ankles,
delivering oxygen
to the muscles,
allowing him to hold on
for hours at a time.
But he's not made
for hanging around.
The loris is a night expert.
Forward-facing eyes give him
stereoscopic vision
for pinpoint depth perception,
and a reflective layer
behind his retina
delivers brilliant
low-light images,
essential for being
a nocturnal predator.
Insects are cold-blooded,
so in the cool of the night
they slow down,
playing right into the hands...
Of the slow loris.
It's more stealth than speed.
Few escape.
Tonight, though,
he's distracted...
By her.
But she's not in heat
and would rather have a bite herself.
She's giving him
the cold shoulder.
No luck this time.
There is a faster
night hunter here,
using a different strategy.
A fishing bat.
He relies not on eyesight,
but on sound.
His high-frequency clicks
bounce back off the water,
helping to echolocate prey.
He can distinguish
between insects
that rest stock-still...
And fish that create
a moving target
when their ripples
break the surface.
With hook-like claws,
he's well equipped to catch fish,
which make up over half
his diet.
A ripple on the surface
reveals the target.
The fishing bat is
in full hunting mode.
He misses.
He circles back.
This time he locks on
to the prey...
And then returns
to the roost
to devour his catch.
Whether hunter or hunted,
raising a family or finding food,
adaptation is key
to surviving the jungle.
Phayre's leaf monkeys spend
almost all their time
in the canopy doing
what they do best...
Eating leaves.
They seldom come down
from the trees,
so when they do,
it's a privileged view.
These rare monkeys are given
the highest protection in China.
And a recent discovery of a much
larger group than normal,
200 strong, is encouraging.
This troop is venturing
into the open
in search of a special treat.
When conditions come together
in the perfect mix,
the leaf monkeys do something
that has never been filmed
in Yunnan before.
Clouds build and boil,
pushed up by the warm air......
Until they reach bursting point.
The rainy season lasts
five months of the year.
The downpour gives birth
to waterfalls
cascading for more than 100 feet.
This water encourages the growth
of mosses, grasses
and other plants.
Rich pickings for our monkeys.
The waterfall is
in this troop's territory,
but they only visit
for one type of plant
when the conditions are perfect.
Today is the day.
100 Feet up
on the wet, sheer rock face,
they feast.
It may just be moss,
but our monkeys are eating
the unusual.
Few herbivores
have a taste for it
because it's so
nutritionally poor.
Exactly what the benefits are
remain a mystery,
but our troop's behavior shows
how adaptable they can be
in this jungle.
Having had their fill,
it's time for a quick drink
before the troop turns
its back to the sun
to dry off.
Time to return
to the treetops
where they belong.
Below the canopy
in a clearing,
an Asiatic black bear.
At over 250 pounds,
his diet consists mainly
of fruit and nuts.
To satisfy his appetite,
he spends much of his day
foraging.
But when our hungry bear
takes a break from eating,
what better way
to spend the time
than to just frolic?
Then, something in the air
grabs his attention.
His eyesight isn't the best.
He relies instead
on his other senses.
He's hearing and smelling bees.
Yunnan is home
to two thirds
of China's honeybee species.
Each one helps to maintain
the area's impressive
plant diversity.
Using her long straw-like tongue
called a proboscis,
she sucks the nectar
out of the flower,
storing it in her honey stomach
for the journey home.
Asian honeybees live in enclosed
cavities, including tree hollows.
Colonies can be 34,000 strong.
Honeybees are superorganisms.
Life in here is about
working together
for the greater good.
Their nest is
an architectural wonder.
The bees build aerial cities
of multiple combs,
arranged parallel
to one another.
A mass of hexagonal cells,
home to the bees' larvae,
pollen and honey.
There are plenty
of bee colonies,
but this tree
has the bear's attention.
Honey drips down the trunk
from an abandoned hive
and tastes wonderful.
A favorite jungle snack
of his.
Within relatively easy reach.
No chance of getting stung.
And he wants more......
Much more.
These bears spend half
of their life in trees.
They're one of the largest
arboreal mammals on the planet.
His strong legs and forearms
make short work of the climb.
While he takes care of the honey.
With a full stomach,
getting down
is a lot trickier
than getting up.
Getting down is not a problem
for our herd.
Arriving again
at their watering hole,
elephants help maintain
this kingdom,
and people, too,
are taking steps
to preserve the stunning array
of plants
and animals
of Yunnan's jungles.
Numbering only 170 individuals
in the early 1990s,
this elephant population
has almost doubled.
Today, this guy is hope
for the future.
He's just a few weeks old.
Completely reliant on mom
for the next 18 months,
he will develop a close bond
with her
until he's about 8 years old.
There is a lot to learn.
Not drowning, for one.
His life story lies ahead.
Many more will be discovered
in China's hidden jungle kingdom.